Discarded artificial satellites.
Tanks jettisoned from shuttles.
使い捨てる[つかいすてる]:to use and then throw away, 人工衛星[じんこうえいせい]:man-made satellite
（ナレーション）
使い捨てられた人工衛星
シャトル:shuttlecock, 切り離す[きりはなす]:to detach/to decapitate/to cut loose, タンク:tank (of liquid)
シャトルが切り離したタンク
ステーション:station, 建造[けんぞう]:building/construction, 廃棄物[はいきぶつ]:waste matter/waste/garbage
ステーション建造時に出た廃棄物
Refuse generated during
space station construction.
This trash, space debris, circles the Earth
at speeds approaching 8 kilometers per second.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, スペース:space (room, area, outer space), デブリ:debris
これら 宇宙のゴミ
スペースデブリは―
秒速[びょうそく]:per second, キロメートル:kilometer/kilometre, 近い[ちかい]:near|close (in time)|close (relationship)||, 速度[そくど]:speed/velocity/rate, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 周り[まわり]:circumference/girth|surroundings, 回る[めぐる]:to go around|to return|to surround|, 回る[まわる]:to turn|to visit several places|to function well|
秒速８キロメートル近い速度で
地球の周りを回っています
デブリ:debris, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, ぶつかる:to strike against/to collide with|to encounter
そんなデブリが
宇宙船とぶつかれば―
Should this debris collide with a spacecraft,
it could result in a terrible accident.
大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to, かねる:to be unable to/to find difficult (unpleasant, awkward, painful) to do|to serve two or more functions or roles simultaneously
大きな事故に つながりかねません
For this reason, mankind has been confronted
by the necessity of collecting this debris.
人々[ひとびと, にんにん]:each person/people/men and women, デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity, 迫る[せまる, せる]:to approach/to draw near|to press (someone for something)
そこで人々は デブリを
回収する必要に迫られました
2075年―
This is a story of 2075, a time in which
this space garbage has become a problem.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||, 時代[じだい]:period|the times|oldness|, 物語[ものがたり]:tale/story/legend
これは 宇宙のゴミが
問題になった時代の物語
Passengers, may we have
your attention please.
（タナベ）はあ～
Don't you think this subtle
floating sensation is great?
微妙[びみょう]:delicate|difficult|doubtful, 微妙[みみょう]:unspeakably wonderful/sublime/exquisite, フワフワ:lightly (floating, drifting, etc.)/buoyantly, 感[かん]:feeling/sensation|interjection, 面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
なんか この微妙な
フワフワ感が面白いですね
無重力[むじゅうりょく]:weightlessness/zero gravity
（フィー）
無重力でもなく １Ｇでもなく？
You mean how it's not zero-G,
and not one-G, either?
妖精[ようせい]:fairy/sprite/elf, 気分[きぶん]:feeling/mood
はい
なんか妖精にでもなった気分です
Yes, ma'am! It feels like I've turned
into a fairy or something!
妖精[ようせい]:fairy/sprite/elf
（ハチマキ）
ケッ 何が妖精だよ
Fairy, my ass.
More like a devil.
悪魔[あくま]:devil|Satan|Māra
…ていうより悪魔
せめて:at least/at most, せめて:offense/offence/method of attack, 小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|, 悪魔[あくま]:devil|Satan|Māra, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
せめて 小悪魔って言ってください
At least make it "cute little imp."
天使[てんし]:angel
あっ 天使でもいいですよ
Oh! "Angel" would be
fine, too.
であっ うわあーっ
使[し]:messenger|police and judicial chief (Heian and Kamakura periods)|klesha (polluting thoughts such as greed, hatred and delusion, which result in suffering)
（ハチマキ）ハハハッ
そら見ろ 堕天使が
Serves ya right,
you fallen angel!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 笑う[わらう]:to laugh|to smile|to sneer|, 助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
先輩
笑ってないで助けてくださいよ
Senpai, stop laughing at me
and help me up...
Well, I'll let you get
Tanabe squared away.
頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
じゃ タナベのことは頼んだ
I have to pop in for a quick visit
to Third Division.
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face
私は 第３事業部に
顔 出さなくちゃならないから
ん？
あっ ありが…
Thank y...
ハハハハ… バーカ
Moron!
子供[こども]:child/children, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 意地悪[いじわる]:malicious/ill-tempered/unkind
何 子供みたいな
意地悪してんですか
What are you, a kid?
Don't tease me like that!
You're the one who's a kid!
Look at you, making such a big deal out of this!
子供[こども]:child/children
（ハチマキ）
お前のほうが子供だってえの
はしゃぐ:to make merry/to frolic/to be in high spirits, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
はしゃぎやがって
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, ガイド:guide/tour guide/conductor, 付ける[つける]:to attach|to furnish (a house with)|to wear||
（タナベ）キィー 先輩だって
ガイドに赤丸 付けてたくせに
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, ガイド:guide/tour guide/conductor, 付ける[つける]:to attach|to furnish (a house with)|to wear||
（タナベ）キィー 先輩だって
ガイドに赤丸 付けてたくせに
（フィー）ハァ…
Big talk from a guy who made all those
red circles in his guide book!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, ガイド:guide/tour guide/conductor, 付ける[つける]:to attach|to furnish (a house with)|to wear||
（タナベ）キィー 先輩だって
ガイドに赤丸 付けてたくせに
♪～
時空[じくう]:space-time, 越える[こえる]:to cross over/to cross|to exceed, 夢を見る[ゆめをみる]:to dream/to have a dream
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
静寂[せいじゃく, しじま]:silence/stillness/quietness, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 抱く[いだく, だく]:to embrace|to harbour (e.g. grudge)|to have sex with|
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
鳥[とり]:bird|bird meat (esp. chicken meat)/fowl, 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
儚い[はかない]:fleeting/transient|empty (dream, etc.), 生命[せいめい]:life/existence, 燃やす[もやす, もす]:to burn
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
幾[いく]:some|many|how many?, 幾[ほとほと]:quite (usu. negative connotation)/utterly/really, 千[せん, ち]:1,000/thousand, 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||
♪幾千の朝に
光[ひかり]:light|illumination|happiness||, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
♪光が向かう場所へ
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
羽ばたく[はばたく]:to flap (wings)|to spread one's wings/to go out into the world
♪羽ばたくだろう
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
願い[ねがい]:desire/wish/request, 放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||
♪願いを放つ時は今
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
果て[はて]:the end/the extremity/the limit, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
フロンティア:frontier
♪フロンティアへ
遠い[とおい]:far/distant
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places
（ハチマキ）
今いる所は―
The level we're on now has various companies
and government administration buildings.
Phase 6
The Lunar Flying Squirrels
いろんな:various, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 官公庁[かんこうちょう]:government administration office
いろんな会社や
官公庁がある
Shopping centers and residential areas
are below that.
商業[しょうぎょう]:commerce/trade/business, 施設[しせつ]:institution/establishment|(army) engineer, 住宅街[じゅうたくがい]:residential area
商業施設や住宅街は
その下だ
要する[ようする]:to need/to demand/to take, 偉[い]:greatness, 偉[えら]:tremendous/huge, いさむ:to be in high spirits/to be encouraged/to be lively
要するに
上のほうがお偉いさんで―
In otherwords, the upper crust are up top,
and the lower classes live below.
下々[しもじも, したじた]:the lower classes/the common people, 地下[ちか]:basement|underground|secret|
下々の者は 地下のほうってわけだ
家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 借りる[かりる]:to borrow/to have a loan|to rent
そういや お前
どこに 家 借りたんだ？
Speaking of which, where's
the place you're renting?
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 借りる[かりる]:to borrow/to have a loan|to rent
課長が借りてくれたので
Well, the Chief rented it for me,
so I don't...
あった
Here it is!
地区[ちく]:district/section/sector, 号室[ごうしつ]:suffix for room numbers
アルノ地区の３の14 ４号室です
Arnould Area, 3-14. Room 4.
途中[とちゅう]:on the way/en route|in the middle of
だったら
途中まで ついてってやるよ
In that case, I'll walk you partway there.
We're headed in the same direction.
行き先[いきさき, ゆきさき]:destination|whereabouts/address, 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
行き先 同じだからな
You're renting a place in
Arnould Area, too, Senpai?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 地区[ちく]:district/section/sector, 家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 借りる[かりる]:to borrow/to have a loan|to rent
先輩もアルノ地区に
家 借りてるんですか？
No, I have an appointment
at the Grand Hotel. It's nearby.
近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly, グラン:large, ホテル:hotel, 待ち合わせる[まちあわせる]:to rendezvous/to meet at a prearranged place and time/to arrange to meet
いや
近くのグランホテルで待ち合わせ
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|, 届け物[とどけもの]:article to be delivered/present
課長に頼まれて 届け物だ
The Chief asked me
to deliver this.
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
（サリバン）
早すぎたんじゃないか？
Aren't we early? We still have
more than two hours.
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||
まだ ２時間以上ある
着付け[きつけ]:dressing (esp. in kimono)/fitting|outer garment (in kabuki), 結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||, かかる:to span/to bridge/to cross, かかる:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang
（チッタ）
着付けって 結構 時間かかるのよ
It takes a while
to get dressed.
Besides, I want to have some time
to unwind after that.
着付ける[きつける]:to put on/to wear|to be used to wearing, 落ち着く[おちつく]:to calm down|to calm down|to settle down (in a location, job, etc.)||, 余裕[よゆう]:surplus/margin|composure, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
それに 着付けてから
落ち着く余裕は欲しいじゃない？
いらっしゃる:to come/to go|is (doing)
（案内係）いらっしゃいませ
Welcome to the hotel.
予約[よやく]:reservation|contract|programming (e.g. a device)
ああ 予約したサリバンですけど
Thanks.
We have a reservation under "Sullivan."
様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 承る[うけたまわる]:to hear/to be told|to receive (order)
（案内係）
サリバン様 承っております
Ah, Sullivan-sama.
We've been expecting you.
荷物[にもつ]:luggage|burden|payload (of a packet, cell, etc.), 預かり[あずかり]:under custody/under supervision|undecided match
では お荷物のお預かりを…
I'll see to your luggage.
You don't need to go to all that trouble.
気張る[きばる]:to strain or exert oneself/to go all out
（サリバン）
そんな気張らなくてもなあ
I'd like to get changed first.
着付け[きつけ]:dressing (esp. in kimono)/fitting|outer garment (in kabuki), 済む[すむ]:to finish|to merely result in something less severe than expected|to feel at ease|
（チッタ）
着付けを済ませておきたいんですが
Of course.
This boy hardly seems like the formal wear type.
向こう[むこう]:opposite side|over there|the other party|, 大した[たいした]:considerable/great/important, 風采[ふうさい]:appearance/air/mien
向こうだって
大した風采じゃないぞ
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department
（フィー）
第２事業部のカーマイケルです
I'm Carmichael, Second Division.
I'm here about the end-of-month balance
sheet for the Graveyard Orbit.
墓場[はかば]:graveyard/cemetery, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 月末[げつまつ, つきずえ]:end of the month, 決算[けっさん]:settlement of accounts/closing accounts/financial results, フィー:phi
墓場軌道の月末決算に…
（チャド）フィー！
- Fee!
配転[はいてん]:reshuffling/job rotation
（フィー）
ん？ ああ こっちに配転？
You transferred here?
I just couldn't keep up with
those lifetime workers.
生え抜き[はえぬき]:native-born/trueborn, かなう:to come true (wish)|to be suited
生え抜きさんには かなわないよ
小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 数字[すうじ]:numeral/figure/digit, 責任[せきにん]:duty/responsibility (incl. supervision of staff)|liability, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
小さい会社でやってきた俺には
数字も責任も大きすぎた
For a guy from a small
company like me, the numbers and responsibility
were too much to handle.
うーん:hmm/well
（フィー）うーん
（チャド）ドルフは どうしてる？
What's Dolf up to
these days?
相変わらず[あいかわらず]:as ever/as usual/the same, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
（フィー）
相変わらずの仕事人間よ
He's still a man
who lives for his job.
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
（チャド）あいつは すごいよな
That man
is amazing.
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, 事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, 立派[りっぱ]:splendid|praiseworthy|legal|
テクノーラみたいな大きなとこでも
事業部長として立派にやってる
He's doing so well
for himself.
He's even a department manager
at a big company like Technora.
Rumor has it that he's in line for
the board of directors, too, right?
取締役[とりしまりやく]:company director/board member, 近い[ちかい]:near|close (in time)|close (relationship)||, うわさ:rumour/rumor/report
取締役も近いって うわさだろう？
うわさ話[うわさばなし]:gossip, 疎い[うとい]:distant/estranged|poorly informed
さあね うわさ話には疎いんだ
I wouldn't know. I don't really
keep up with the gossip.
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength), 昔[むかし]:olden days/former
すごいよな あいつは
昔から すごかったもんな
That man is something else. He always
was amazing, even in the old days.
なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something
俺なんかとは違うんだよな
The two of us are like
night and day...
食事[しょくじ]:meal|to eat, 昔話[むかしばなし]:old tale/folk tale|reminiscence
ああ よかったら食事でもどう？
昔話でもしようよ
Say, why don't we get some dinner or
something? We can talk about old times.
ウヘエ…
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 連れ込む[つれこむ]:to bring (somebody into a place), やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
（男性）てめえ 俺のいねえ間に
また連れ込みやがったな
You bitch! You brought a man home
while I was away again, didn't you?!
If you don't like it, try
being at home for once!
嫌[いや, や]:disagreeable/detestable/unpleasant, ちっと:a little bit|a little while, 家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, なさる:to do
（女性）それが嫌なら
ちっとは 家(うち)にいなさいよ
（男性）何だ ごらあ
- What did you say?!
Shut up,
you deadbeat!
いわね:rock, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
（女性）
うるっさいわね この駄目男
（男性）ヒヒヒ… あっ
（タナベ）へ？
ヒエー ヘッヘー
着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow, 新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family
着いたぞ お前の新しい家
Well, here we are.
Welcome to your new home.
（タナベ）ええ？
（ハチマキ）じゃあな
See ya.
（タナベ）
ええっ もう行っちゃうんですか？
You're leaving already?!
ホテル:hotel
言ったろ？ ４時にホテルだって
I told you, I have to be
at the hotel by four.
うわあっ
うーん:hmm/well
（ハチマキ）んっ
（タナベ）うーん…
普通[ふつう]:general|normally|local train
（ハチマキ）ほら見ろ
普通のとこじゃないか
See, what did I tell you?
The place is perfectly normal.
Since you've already come this far, walk me
the rest of the way to my room, okay?
部屋[へや]:room|apartment|stable, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
ここまで来たんですから
部屋まで ついてきてくださいよ
You have plenty of time
before 4 o'clock, so...
４時までなら…
（タナベ）えっ？
（ハチマキ）ん？
変[へん]:strange|unexpected|change||
ほ… ほら なんか変ですよ ここ
S-See? There's something
weird about this place!
Don't let it get to you, It's just
a strange door chime, that's all.
気にする[きにする]:to mind (negative nuance)/to care about/to worry, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different, ドアチャイム:door chime/doorbell
気にすんな
ちょっと変わったドアチャイムだよ
What about
those, then?!
じゃあ あれは？
（ハチマキ）あ？ まき… びし？
Ninja... caltrops?
とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light)
（小源太(こげんた)）そのとおり！
（タナベ･ハチマキ）えっ？
Exactly right!
Your eyes are indeed sharp,
my good visitors!
見破る[みやぶる]:to see through another's thoughts/to have a sharp eye/to penetrate, 来訪者[らいほうしゃ]:client/visitor/caller
（小源太）
よくぞ 見破った 来訪者どもよ
あっぱれ:splendid/praiseworthy|well done!, 褒める[ほめる]:to praise/to admire/to speak well of someone
（小源太）
まずは あっぱれと褒めておこう
First, allow me to offer you
my compliments.
Um, Tanabe?
What's that look like to you?
見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
（ハチマキ）
なあ タナベ あれ 何に見える？
忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.), 以外[いがい]:with the exception of/excepting, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
（タナベ）何…
忍者以外の何に見えるんですか？
What do you mean?
What else could he be but a ninja?
ひける:to close/to be over|to lose one's nerve, なさる:to do
（小源太）
おひけえなすってえ
Hark and attend
my words!
I am a Koga ninja.
I am known
as Kogenta of the Mist.
拙者[せっしゃ]:I (primarily used by samurai)/me, 忍び[しのび]:stealth|travelling incognito (traveling)|ninjutsu||, 霞[かすみ]:haze (esp. in spring)/mist|dimness (of sight), 小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|, 申す[もうす]:to say/to be called|to do, ざんす:to be
拙者 甲賀(こうが)の忍び
霞(かすみ)の小源太と申す者でござんす
本人[ほんにん]:the person himself
ほらほら
本人も ああ言ってますし
Hey, you hear that?
He says so, too!
ひける:to close/to be over|to lose one's nerve, なさる:to do, 忍び[しのび]:stealth|travelling incognito (traveling)|ninjutsu||
“おひけえなすって”は
忍びじゃねえだろ
It wasn't ninjas who used to say
"Hark and attend my words"...
キエーッ とわっ
とうっ！
十字[じゅうじ]:cross/crossed/cruciform
伊賀(いが) 十字撃ち
Iga cross attack!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 本物[ほんもの]:genuine article/real thing/real deal
（タナベ･ハチマキ）ええっ！？
（タナベ）先輩 本物ですよ
Senpai! He's the real thing!
Yeah, a real head case.
本物[ほんもの]:genuine article/real thing/real deal, 変態[へんたい]:transformation/metamorphosis|abnormality
ああ 本物の変態だな
逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
逃げろ！
（タナベ）えっ
Let's get outta here!
冗談[じょうだん, ぎだん]:jest/joke/funny story
（ハチマキ）冗談だろ おあっ
（タナベ）うええっ
You gotta be
kidding me!
クアッハ:quagga (extinct South African zebra) (Equus quagga quagga)
（小源太）
カッカッカッカッ… クアッハ～
楽しい[たのしい]:enjoyable/fun
よかったな タナベ
楽しそうなとこじゃないか
Good for you, Tanabe!
Looks like you've got some fun neighbors!
（タナベ）どこがですか！
What makes you
say that?!
Well, I'll let you
get acquainted!
じゃあ 俺は これで
How can you be so
irresponsible, Senpai?!
無責任[むせきにん]:irresponsibility, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（タナベ）無責任ですよ 先輩！
うっ…
忍法[にんぽう]:ninja arts, 壁[かべ, へき]:wall|barrier|Chinese "Wall" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 走り[はしり]:running|gliding|first (harvest) of the season||
（紅右近(くれないうこん)）忍法 壁走り！
Ninpo Wall-walking Technique!
変[へん]:strange|unexpected|change||
（タナベ）また変なのが出たー
Another weirdo showed up!
（ハチマキ）こっちだ
（タナベ）うっ うう…
This way!
逃す[のがす]:to miss (e.g. a chance)|to set free|to fail to ..., ごわす:(Satsuma) to be
（太郎坊(たろうぼう)）
逃しはしないでごわす
There is no escape
from us!
（ハチマキ）げえっ
（タナベ）ええっ
Have a taste of the astonishing
Human Throwing Star!
食らう[くらう]:to eat/to drink|to receive (e.g. a blow), 驚愕[きょうがく]:surprise/fright/shock, 手裏剣[しゅりけん]:shuriken/small throwing blade/small edged weapon often used for throwing
（太郎坊）
食らいませ 驚愕(きょうがく)人間手裏剣！
如意[にょい]:one's wishes|ceremonial sceptre used by monks when reciting sutras (scepter), 棒[ぼう]:pole/rod/stick
（三次(さんじ)）如意棒！
Iron cudgel!
だああーっ
Finishing move!
Flying Fans!
必殺[ひっさつ]:bringing certain death/deadly/knockout (blow), 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan, 舞[まい]:dancing/dance
（幻之丞(げんのじょう)）必殺 扇の舞！
はいはい はいはい はいはい
Hup hup hup hup!
はいはい はいはい はいはい…
Pretend you don't
see him!
（ハチマキ）
見ないふり 見ないふり
いでる:to go/to come
（地雷也(じらいや)）
いでよ がま五右衛門(ごえもん)
Come forth,
Gamagoemon!
（人形）ア～
（ハチマキ）
だあ 知らんぷり 知らんぷり
Ignore him, ignore him!
チョー:super-/ultra-/hyper-
（チュン）
アチョー チョチョチョー チョー
That's strange, it looks like
some of them aren't ninjas!
忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.), 混じる[まじる]:to be mixed/to be blended with/to associate with, 混じる[こんじる]:to be mixed in with/to blend with, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
（タナベ）なんか忍者じゃない人も
混じってるみたいですけど
Seeing ninjas running around in
the first place is what's strange!
忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.), 時点[じてん]:point in time/occasion, おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
（ハチマキ）
忍者がいる時点でおかしいだろ
（課長）ええっ 何だって？
Huh? What was that?
アパート:apartment building/apartment block/apartment house
だから タナベのアパートだよ
I'm talking about Tanabe's apartment!
You rented it out, didn't you?!
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 借りる[かりる]:to borrow/to have a loan|to rent
課長が借りたんだろ？
ああ もう…
日本人[にほんじん, にっぽんじん]:Japanese person/Japanese people, おすすめ:recommendation/advice/suggestion
（課長）ああ
日本人に おすすめって言うから
That's right.
It came highly recommended for Japanese people.
おすすめ:recommendation/advice/suggestion
（ハチマキ）おすすめじゃねえよ！
- Recommended, my ass!
ああ もう…
（課長）ハッちゃん
今日の４時って言ったよね？
It told you it's at 4:00 today, right, Hachi?
It's already 3:30 over there.
時半[じはん]:about an hour/short time|half past (the hour)
そっちは もう３時半…
- I've got bigger things
to worry about!
場合[ばあい]:case/situation
そんな場合じゃねえって
ああ ああ… ぐう
先方[せんぽう, さきかた]:companion|destination|person in front, 先方[さきがた]:a little while ago, 話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language)
（課長）いやあ でも
先方には話しちゃったからさあ
But I've already spoken
to the other party, and...
Look, I'm trying to
tell you that...
だから… おおっ？
忍法[にんぽう]:ninja arts, 電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device), ボックス:box, 舞[まい]:dancing/dance
忍法 電話ボックスの舞！
Ninpo, Flying Phonebox
Technique!
（タナベ）うそ！
No way!
（ハチマキ）どわあ
（タナベ）ええっ
遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|
（サリバン）
遅いですな 星野(ほしの)さんは
Hoshino-san sure is late...
着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow
（仲人）今日 月に着くって
言ってましたから―
They said that he would be arriving
on the moon today, so it's possible that
his flight was delayed.
便[びん]:flight (e.g. airline flight)|mail|opportunity, 便[べん]:convenience/service|excreta (esp. faeces), 遅れる[おくれる]:to be late/to be delayed/to fall behind schedule
便が遅れてるのかも
杯[さかずき, さかづき]:sake cup/cup for alcoholic beverages, 杯[はい, はた]:sake cup|counter for cupfuls|counter for ships, octopuses and squid, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
うん… お水 もう１杯ください！
Another water over here,
please!
ホテル:hotel, いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good, っつう:meaning/called/said
カーッ 俺は４時には ホテルに
いなきゃいけないっつうのに～
Damn it, I need to be
at the hotel by four!
超絶[ちょうぜつ]:transcendence/excellence/superiority, 忍法[にんぽう]:ninja arts
超絶忍法 七転八倒
Transcendent ninpo!
Tossing in Agony Technique!
横綱[よこづな]:yokozuna (highest rank in sumo)/grand champion|best in its field, 万歳[まんざい]:door-to-door comedic duo, 万歳[ばんざい, ばんぜい]:crying "banzai" (or raising one's hands in the banzai gesture)|something worthy of celebration|giving up||
（忍者たち）横綱万歳！
Yokozuna, banzai!
（三次･小源太）いよお
（ハチマキ）いいっ…
What the hell are
you people thinking?!
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
何 考えてんだ！
（一同）おお～！
（忍者たちの拍手）
Roast pork noodles!
チャーシュー:roasted pork fillet (often used in ramen), 麺[めん]:noodles|flour
（ハチマキ）チャーシュー麺！
いっ がっ うぐっ
かげん:(moon's) last quarter, かげん:lower limit|infimum
いいかげんにしろよ お前ら！
Give it a rest,
you lunatics!
風[ふり]:swing|appearance|pretence (pretense)||, 風[かぜ]:wind|manner|cold, 馬[うま, いま]:horse|horse racing|promoted bishop, まんずる:to be conceited, 固め[かため]:hardening|pledge|defense, 固め[かため]:hardness/firmness
（小源太）風馬 まんじ固め
Wind demon,
closed gammadion!
玉屋[たまや]:jeweler
（紅右近）玉(たま)屋
Tamaya!
Bravo!
あっぱれ:splendid/praiseworthy|well done!
（幻之丞）あっぱれ
（タナベ）えっ？
（忍者たち）ラリホー
Rally ho!
（チュン）
あやっ あの男がいない
Huh? That man
is gone!
消えうせる[きえうせる]:to disappear/to vanish|to die
どこへ消えうせた？
Where has he
disappeared to?!
Behind us!
後ろ[うしろ]:back/behind/rear
後ろだ！
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
先輩！
Senpai!
I've had about enough
of you guys!
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself, 許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
（ハチマキ）
てめえら もう許さん！
Secret arts!
奥義[おうぎ, おくぎ]:secret techniques/inner mysteries/esoterica
奥義！
The white rabbit!
因幡(いなば) の―
Of!
し ろ う さ ぎ
I-n-a-b-a!
I'm outta here,
Tanabe.
あっ
（ハチマキ）いっ げえっ この！
Aw, man!
You little...
（忍者たち）やられた
You got us!
ああ？
Truly, the way of the warrior
is to be found in death...
武士道[ぶしどう]:Bushido/samurai code of chivalry, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
武士道とは 死ぬことと見つけたり
ぬふっ
（ハチマキ）かあ あ…
ウフフ:giggle/chuckle/titter
（リュシー）ウフフ
But aren't the people in
Debris Section a little rowdy?
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 騒がしい[さわがしい]:noisy/boisterous|turbulent (era, etc.)
でも デブリ課の人って
騒がしくありません？
（チェンシン）アハッ
He may not look it, but ever since Hachi met
that new girl, Tanabe, he's really settled down.
後輩[こうはい]:junior (at work, school, etc.)/younger people/younger student
あれでも タナベさんっていう
後輩ができて ハチとかも―
随分[ずいぶん]:very/extremely|contemptible, おとなしい:obedient/docile/quiet
随分おとなしくなった…
（ハチマキ）キエーッ！
胡蝶[こちょう]:butterfly, 舞[まい]:dancing/dance
胡蝶(こちょう)の舞！
Flying butterfly!
Impertinent swine!
おのれ:oneself (itself, etc.)|I/me, ちょこざい:impertinence, 尋常[じんじょう]:common/usual
（小源太）おのれ ちょこざいな
（幻之丞）いざ尋常に
Fight us...
...fair and square!
勝負[しょうぶ]:victory or defeat/match/contest
（紅右近）勝負勝負
（三次）猿飛
Flying monkey!
Ready... fight!
はっけよい:phrase shouted by a referee when both rikishi have stopped moving
（太郎坊）はっけよい
（地雷也）ゲロヨン
Ribbit!
（チュン）アチョー アチョー
ニッ アチョー！
Senpai!
Wait for me!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（タナベ）先輩 待ってくださいよ
えーっと:let me see/well/errr ...
えーっと…
（リュシー）はあ…
Um...
（ハチマキ）いやあーっ！
ふんんんっ くっ ふっ
アチャチャチャチャチャー！
むっつり:sullenly/taciturnly|taciturn person
（ハチマキ）ていっ
（太郎坊）むっつり
Backwards pivot throw!
ほっ
（ハチマキ）ぎゃっ
のこる:to remain/to be left
のこった
He's still fighting?
我が[わが]:my/our/one's own, 妖術[ようじゅつ]:black magic/black art/witchcraft
ならば 我が妖術で
In that case, I'll use
my black magic to...
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 番[ばん]:number (in a series)|(one's) turn|watch|, 番[つがい]:(one) pair (e.g. of birds)/brace|joint
（紅右近）
待て待て 次 俺の番だろ
Wait, wait!
It's my turn next!
Hey, would this be a good time
to use my smoke bombs?
煙玉[けむりだま]:smoke bomb/smokebomb
ねえねえ
煙玉 使ってもいいかな？
忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.), まんだら:mandala/Buddhist visual schema of the enlightened mind
（地雷也）
あれやってみようよ 忍者まんだら
No, let's try out
the Ninja Mandala!
（ハチマキ）どわあーっ！
秘奥[ひおう]:secrets/mysteries, 義[ぎ]:morality|meaning|teachings||, 大玉[おおだま]:large ball/giant ball (e.g. as pushed by competing teams in a school sports day), 転がし[ころがし]:rolling (something)|fishing with multiple hooks on a weighted line|repeatedly buying and selling
秘奥義 大玉 あっ 転がしぃ
Secret arts!
Giant Rolling Ball!
That's some serious ninpo!
- Show us, show us!
ありゃ:oh/ah/I'll be darned, 大技[おおわざ, たいぎょう]:bold move/great task or feat
（忍者たち）ありゃ 大技だ
Senpai, what the heck
are you thinking?!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
先輩 何 考えてんですか？
あれ？ ん？
Huh?
ぎゃあ:yikes!/eek!|monkey screech
（ハチマキ）どわっ ぎゃああーっ
（忍者たち）うわあっ
Senpai!
（タナベ）せんぱーい！
返事[へんじ]:reply/answer/response, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
返事してください 先輩！
Say something, Senpai!
んっ うっ んっ んっ
んっ ぐっ うっ…
はっ… あ？
A one and a two
and a heave-ho!
えんや:charming/bewitching/coquettish, どっこいしょ:heigh-hoh/heave-ho|used as a meaningless word in a song for rhythm
（一同）
えんや こら どっこいしょ
Senpai!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
先輩！
Are you alive?
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||
生きてますか？
（ハチマキ）あ ああ… あ？
We're sorry.
（地雷也）すみません
The landlord said that
a Japanese person was coming...
大家[おおや]:landlord/landlady, 大家[たいか]:master|mansion|rich family, 日本人[にほんじん, にっぽんじん]:Japanese person/Japanese people
大家さんから
日本人が来るって聞いたら―
I guess we got a little
too enthusiastic.
うれしい:happy/glad/pleasant
なんだか うれしくなっちゃって
Plus, you were wearing the
hachimaki headband of a ninja.
忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.), しるし:mark/sign|symbol, しるし:decapitated head of an enemy, ハチマキ:headband
（小源太）
忍者のしるしのハチマキもしてるし
本場[ほんば]:home/habitat|authentic, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
（太郎坊）
本場の人に見てもらいたくて つい
We wanted a real, live Japanese
person to see our moves.
忍法[にんぽう]:ninja arts
どうですか？ 僕らの忍法
What did you think
of our ninpo?
日本人[にほんじん, にっぽんじん]:Japanese person/Japanese people, ブラック:black, ベルト:belt (waist, seat, etc.)/strap, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
日本人は みんな ブラックベルトを
持ってるんですよね
Everybody in Japan
has a black belt, right?
Once you reach the upper ninja ranks,
you get to marry a geisha girl, right?
上忍[じょうにん]:Ninja clan master/highest-ranking ninja, ガール:girl, 結婚[けっこん]:marriage
上忍になると ゲイシャガールと
結婚できるんでしょ？
Where did you people
learn this garbage?
教わる[おそわる]:to be taught (by)/to learn from
それ 誰に教わった？
Miss Kunoichi.
くのいち:female ninja|woman
（小源太）ミス くのいち
（タナベ）ん？
We bid you welcome to
Maison de Yashiki.
メゾン:house, ようこそ:welcome!/nice to see you!
メゾン･ド･ヤシキにようこそ
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals, 住む[すむ]:to live (of humans)/to reside/to inhabit
えっ…
（太郎坊）あそこに住むんでしょ？
You're living there, right?
I'm Crimson Ukon, room 3.
My real name is Macleod.
号室[ごうしつ]:suffix for room numbers, 紅[くれない, べに]:deep red/crimson|rouge, 紅[あか]:red|red-containing colour (e.g. brown, pink, orange)|Red (i.e. communist)||, 本名[ほんみょう, ほんめい]:real name
俺 ３号室の紅右近
本名はマクロード
伴天連[ばてれん, パテレン]:Portuguese Jesuits (in Japan in the 16th century)|Christianity/Christian, 幻[まぼろし]:phantom/vision/illusion, 之[これ]:this (indicating an item near the speaker, the action of the speaker, or the current topic)|this person (usu. indicating someone in one's in-group)|now||, 之[の]:possessive particle, 号室[ごうしつ]:suffix for room numbers
伴天連幻之丞 ３号室です
Gennojo the Missionary. Room 3.
Sanji the Monkey. Room 3.
猿[さる, サル]:monkey (esp. the Japanese macaque, Macaca fuscata)|sly person|idiot||, 猿[ましら, まし]:monkey (esp. the Japanese macaque, Macaca fuscata)/ape/non-human primate, 三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 号室[ごうしつ]:suffix for room numbers
猿の三次 ３号室
Jiraiya of Hida. Room 3.
地雷[じらい]:land mine/booby trap|topic that sets one off (esp. based on previous experience), 也[なり]:to be (an affirmation)|to be (location)|sum of money (used to express an exact sum on a receipt, envelope, certificate, etc.), 号室[ごうしつ]:suffix for room numbers
飛騨の地雷也 ３号室
号室[ごうしつ]:suffix for room numbers, ドラゴン:dragon (as depicted in Western myths), チュン:chirp/cheep, チュン:red dragon tile
３号室のドラゴン･チュン
Dragon Chung! Room 3!
皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything, 号室[ごうしつ]:suffix for room numbers
皆さん ３号室？
You all live
in room 3?
（ハチマキ）うう…
（現場監督）こらあ！
（ハチマキ･タナベ）あっ？
Hey!
You snuck in here again,
didn't you?!
勝手[かって]:one's own convenience|surroundings|convenience||, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
（現場監督）
お前ら また勝手に入りやがって！
先日[せんじつ]:the other day/a few days ago
（小源太）すいませーん
（地雷也）先日はどうも
We're sorry!
- Thanks for the work
the other day!
Feel free to
call on us again!
くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（幻之丞）
よかったら また使ってくださーい
人手[ひとで, ヒトデ]:starfish/sea star|northern Pacific seastar (Asterias amurensis), 人手[ひとで]:someone else's hands|hand (worker)|labor|, 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient
（現場監督）
ヘッ 人手は足りてるよ！
I have all the people I need!
（三次）そっすか すいません
Oh, you do?
Sorry!
Sorry to bother you!
お邪魔[おじゃま]:hindrance/intrusion
（チュン）お邪魔しました
こないだ:the other day/lately/recently, 工事[こうじ]:construction work/construction/work (related to construction, e.g. painting, concrete-pouring, etc.), 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to
（紅右近）こないだ
工事の仕事 手伝ったんだ
We helped out on a construction
job there a while ago.
忍法[にんぽう]:ninja arts, 使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful
（三次）
ほら 俺たち忍法 使えるだろ？
We can use ninja ninpo techniques, right?
That's why they came to us.
頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
だから頼まれてさ
（タナベ）へえ
（店主）うん？ あんたら！
Hey, you! You better do something
about your cleaning bill!
たまる:to collect/to gather/to save, たまる:to be saved up (e.g. money)
たまってるツケ
どうなってるんだい？
We're sorry, Onee-san.
We'll pay you next month for sure.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, おねえさん:elder sister|(vocative) young lady, 来月[らいげつ]:next month, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily
ああ 悪いね おねえさん
来月には必ず
払う[はらう]:to pay (e.g. money, bill)|to brush off|to drive away (e.g. one's competitors)||, 預かる[あずかる]:to look after|to take charge of|to reserve (judgment), 服[ふく]:clothes (esp. Western clothes)|counter for doses of medicine, gulps of tea, drags of a cigarette, etc., 服[ぶく]:mourning clothes|mourning/period of mourning, 渡す[わたす]:to ferry across (e.g. a river)|to lay across|to hand over
払ってくれないと
預かってる服も渡せないよ
If you don't pay up, you're not getting back
the clothes you left here!
頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|, 明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future, 面接[めんせつ]:interview (e.g. for a job)
（小源太）
ええっ 頼むよ 明日も面接で
Have a heart! I have another
job interview tomorrow!
You'll just get turned down again, right?
Suit or no suit, it'll end the same way!
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best, 落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||
（店主）
どうせ また落ちるんだろ？
スーツ:suit, なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something, 着る[きる]:to wear (in modern Japanese, from the shoulders down)/to put on|to bear (guilt, etc.), 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
スーツなんか
着ても着なくても同じさ
格好[かっこう, かっこ]:shape|appearance|state||
その格好で
行けばいいじゃないか！
So you can just go there
dressed in that getup!
忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.), ごっこ:playing at (something)/game of make-believe/something done together
（男性）
お前ら また忍者ごっこか？
Playing ninja again,
are we?
Hurry up and
get a job!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
早く 仕事 見つけろよ
（一同）うっ うう…
（タナベ）ん？
（ハチマキ）ん…
This is an announcement from the municipal
offices of Mare Tranquilitatis City.
静か[しずか]:quiet|slow|calm, 市政[しせい]:municipal government, 本部[ほんぶ]:headquarters/head office/main office, お知らせ[おしらせ]:notice/notification
（アナウンス）静(しず)かの海(うみ)市
市政本部よりお知らせします
Beginning at 2100 hours today,
there will be...
本日[ほんじつ]:today
本日 21時より…
遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|
すいません 遅くなりました
I'm sorry I'm so late.
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief
ああ そうそう
うちの課長から これ…
Oh, right. I have something
from my section chief.
Here.
Oh, my! This is a "get-acquainted gift"
from Hoshino-san!
（仲人）まあ ほら これ
近づき[ちかづき]:acquaintance, しるし:mark/sign|symbol, しるし:decapitated head of an enemy
星野さんから
お近づきのしるしにって
開ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 開ける[ひらける]:to become opened up|to develop|to be enlightened
開けてみて 開けてみて
Open it, open it!
あっ いや その…
Um, I wasn't
the one who...
きれい:pretty/lovely|clean, ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be
（チッタ）きれい！
ありがとうございます
It's beautiful!
Thank you so much!
Um, I didn't...
いや 俺は…
（仲人）星野さん
Hoshino-san,
this is Citta Sullivan-san.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is)
こちら チッタ･サリバンさん
はあ
Uh...
転勤[てんきん]:job transfer/job relocation/intra-company transfer, お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, わざわざ:expressly/specially/doing something especially rather than incidentally
（仲人）転勤するお父さんについて
わざわざ月まで来たの
She came all the way to the moon with
her father when he was transferred here.
You seldom see such devotion
in children these days, do you?
今どき[いまどき]:these days/nowadays|at this time (of the day), 珍しい[めずらしい]:unusual|new|fine (e.g. gift), 親孝行[おやこうこう]:filial piety, 娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman)
今どき珍しい
親孝行な娘さんでしょう？
Right...
（ハチマキ）ええ
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 社[やしろ]:shrine (usually Shinto), 社[しゃ]:company|regional Chinese god of the earth (or a village built in its honour)|counter for companies, shrines, etc., 勤め[つとめ]:service/duty|Buddhist religious services
（仲人）こちら 星野八郎太(はちろうた)さん
テクノーラ社にお勤めなの
This is Hoshino Hachirota-san.
He works for Technora.
My, that's a large company.
I bet you have a steady income.
大企業[だいきぎょう]:large company/enterprise, 生活[せいかつ]:living/life (one's daily existence)/livelihood, 安定[あんてい]:stability/steadiness/equilibrium
（サリバン）いやあ 大企業だ
生活も安定している
よろしく:well/properly|best regards, 頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
よろしく頼むよ 星野君
It's a pleasure to meet you, Hoshino-kun.
Now, then, we should give these two
youngsters some time to themselves!
若い[わかい]:young|immature|low (number), 同士[どうし, どし]:fellow/mutual/companion
じゃあ あとは
若い人同士ということで
（ハチマキ）でえっ おい！
Wha...? Hey!
Do you like roses?
Now that you mention it, I hear that they have...
a Chinese-style garden on the first floor.
いや あの…
Wait, um...
日本[にほん, にっぽん]:Japan, 大好き[だいすき]:loveable/very likeable/like very much
私 日本って 大好きなんです
I love everything
about Japan.
Huh?
えっ…
いや だから…
Look, I think
there's been a...
I'm sorry, I'll only
be a minute.
失礼[しつれい, しつらい]:discourtesy|Excuse me|to leave|
すいません ちょっと失礼します
Hey, uh...
（ハチマキ）
えっ あの… なんで？
What's going on?
Honestly, thank you for finding
such an excellent match!
ほんと:truth/reality|proper, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be
（サリバン）いやあ ほんとに
いい話をありがとうございます
Think nothing of it. Your daughter
is quite lovely, after all.
いいえ:no/nay|well, 娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman), きれい:pretty/lovely|clean
（仲人）
いいえ いいえ 娘さんもきれい…
Those two are just
getting started!
ウーン:hmm/well, 絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, ものにする:to get/to secure|to learn
（チッタ）
ウーン 絶対ものにしなくっちゃ！
I'm gonna make
this one work!
皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything, 号室[ごうしつ]:suffix for room numbers
（タナベ）
本当に皆さん ３号室なんですね
You really do all live
here in room 3, huh?
恥ずかしい[はずかしい]:shy/ashamed|disgraceful, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., 我々[われわれ]:we, 失業者[しつぎょうしゃ]:unemployed person
（小源太）お恥ずかしい話
我々は失業者なんですよ
It's embarrassing to say it,
but we're all unemployed.
はあ
Oh...
We don't have jobs, so we
have a lot of spare time.
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 毎日[まいにち]:every day, 退屈[たいくつ]:tedium/boredom
（小源太）仕事がないから
毎日 毎日 退屈でね
That's how we ended up getting
hooked on ninja movies.
忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.), ムービー:movie, ハマる:to fit|to be fit for (a job, etc.)|to fall into||
そのとき
忍者ムービーにハマりまして
重力[じゅうりょく]:gravity/gravitation/gravitational pull, 忍法[にんぽう]:ninja arts
（地雷也）重力６分の１だから
できちゃうんですよ 忍法
The gravity is 1/6 G, so you
can do ninpo techniques here!
最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, 働く[はたらく]:to work|to function|to commit (e.g. a crime)|
（三次）
あっ でも最初は働いてたんだよ
Oh! We did have jobs
at first, though.
We were brought here by a businessman who
asked us if we wanted helium-3 extraction jobs.
ヘリウム:helium (He), 採取[さいしゅ]:picking/collecting/harvesting, 誘う[さそう, いざなう]:to invite/to ask|to tempt
月でヘリウム３の採取を
やらないかって誘われたんです
稼ぎ[かせぎ]:earnings, 平たい[ひらたい]:flat/even|plain (speech, etc.), 出稼ぎ[でかせぎ]:working away from home
いい稼ぎになるからって
平たく言えば出稼ぎです
He said the money
would be good.
To make a long story short,
we left home to find work.
それで月に
And that's what brought you
to the moon...
いどむ:to challenge/to throw down the gauntlet|to pressure someone for sex, 子供[こども]:child/children, 生まれる[うまれる]:to be born
おいどんは
３人目の子供 生まれた
My wife and I had just had
our third baby...
事業[じぎょう, ことわざ]:project/enterprise|act, 失敗[しっぱい]:failure/mistake/blunder
え？
（チュン）事業に失敗しまして
My business had gone belly up.
I had put up collateral for a friend.
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, 保証人[ほしょうにん]:guarantor/bondsman
友達の保証人になって
I needed the money.
お金[おかね]:money, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
お金 必要だったんですよ
I had such big dreams...
夢[ゆめ]:dream, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great
夢は大きかったなあ
But the businessman I told you about
skipped town with our pay.
口を利く[くちをきく]:to speak/to utter|to mediate, 業者[ぎょうしゃ]:trader/merchant|manufacturer
しかし
口を利いてくれた業者が―
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 給料[きゅうりょう]:salary/wages, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, ドロン:absconding/taking oneself off/slipping out (home) unnoticed early (e.g. from work, out of parties, etc.)
私たちの給料と一緒に
ドロンしまして―
あおり:gust (of wind)|influence, あおり:saddle flap, 食らう[くらう]:to eat/to drink|to receive (e.g. a blow), 我々[われわれ]:we
あおりを食らって 我々はく…
We took the fall for it,
and they fired us.
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
また探せばいいじゃないですか
Then you should look
for new ones!
Like ilmenite mining
or working the drydocks!
イルメナイト:ilmenite, 造船[ぞうせん]:shipbuilding, ドック:dock
イルメナイト掘りとか
造船ドックとか
But you need worker visas
to get a job, right?
働く[はたらく]:to work|to function|to commit (e.g. a crime)|, 就業[しゅうぎょう]:employment/starting work, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
でも 働くには
就業ビザが必要でしょう？
観光[かんこう]:sightseeing
俺たちって
観光ビザで入ってるから
We came here on tourist visas.
業者[ぎょうしゃ]:trader/merchant|manufacturer, 任せ[まかせ]:leaving everything up to someone else
（小源太）ビザのことまで
業者任せにしてた―
（タナベ）え？
It was our own fault for letting that
businessman handle our visas, too...
我々[われわれ]:we, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
我々が悪いんですよ
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, 金[おうごん, こがね]:gold, 金[かね, かな]:money|metal
（地雷也）地球に帰る金もなくて
We don't have the money
to go back to Earth...
アルバイト:part-time job/side job, 食いつなぐ[くいつなぐ]:to ration out and survive on (some food)|to eke out a living
（三次）アルバイトで
なんとか食いつないでるんだ
We manage to keep ourselves fed
by taking odd jobs...
（タナベ）ああ…
やっぱ:too/also|still
い… いやあ やっぱ―
H-Hey, having a kunoichi here really
brightens things up, doesn't it?
Note: 'kunoichi' means female ninja.
くのいち:female ninja|woman, 華やぐ[はなやぐ]:to become brilliant/to become cheerful
くのいちがいると
パッと華やぐよね
くのいち:female ninja|woman
うん くのいち いいよね
Yeah, kunoichis
are the best.
It's dull with nobody
but guys around.
地味[じみ]:plain/simple/subdued, 地味[ちみ]:soil fertility/product of the soil
男だけだと地味だし
A name! We have to think of
a name for Tanabe-san!
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
名前 名前 考えなくっちゃ
タナベさんの
Let's make it something flowery
this time!
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, 明るい[あかるい]:bright|cheerful|familiar (with)|, 胡蝶[こちょう]:butterfly
今度は明るいやつにしよう
“シロガネ”とか“胡蝶”とか
Like Shirogane or Kocho.
"This time"?
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently
今度？
Yeah! We used to...
ああ 前は あっ…
My wife used to act
as our kunoichi.
以前[いぜん]:ago/since/before, 妻[つま]:wife|my dear|garnish (esp. one served with sashimi)|, 妻[め]:female/woman|wife, くのいち:female ninja|woman
（小源太）以前は私の妻が
くのいちをやってくれてたんです
妻[つま]:wife|my dear|garnish (esp. one served with sashimi)|, 妻[め]:female/woman|wife, ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case)
いや もう妻ではありませんね
No, I suppose she isn't
my wife anymore...
出ていきました
She left me.
I can't say
that I blame her.
しかたない:it can't be helped/it's inevitable/it's no use
しかたないですよ
一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 養う[やしなう]:to support|to bring up|to adopt (a child)||
ホレた女一人
養えないんですから
After all, I can't even support
the woman I love.
（一同）うう…
An emergency has been declared
in Level E, West Sector 4.
パトカー:patrol car
（タナベ）パトカー？
A police car?
Isn't that an ambulance?
救急車[きゅうきゅうしゃ]:ambulance
（三次）救急車じゃない？
An evacuation advisory has been issued
for the East and North sectors.
東[あずま, あづま]:eastern Japan (esp. Kamakura or Edo, from perspective of Kyoto or Nara)|east|six-stringed Japanese zither|, 東[ひがし, ひむかし]:east, 地区[ちく]:district/section/sector, および:and/as well as, および:finger/toe/digit, 北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles
（アナウンス）
東地区および北地区に―
No, it's the fire department train.
消防[しょうぼう]:fire fighting|fire department/fire brigade, 列車[れっしゃ]:train (ordinary)
いや 消防列車だ
避難[ひなん]:taking refuge/finding shelter/evacuation, 勧告[かんこく]:advice/counsel/remonstrance, 発令[はつれい]:official announcement/proclamation
避難勧告が
発令されています
最高[さいこう]:most/highest|best, 層[そう]:layer|sheaf|storey (of a building), 暑い[あつい]:hot (weather, etc.)/warm
（男性）ただでさえ
最高層は暑いってのによ
Stand back!
It's dangerous!
消防署[しょうぼうしょ]:fire station, 員[いん]:member, 下がる[さがる]:to come down|to hang|to move back||, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one, 危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk
（消防署員１）
下がってください 危険です
Hey, do something about
those onlookers!
消防署[しょうぼうしょ]:fire station, 員[いん]:member, やじ馬[やじうま, ヤジうま]:curious onlookers/rubbernecks
（消防署員２）
ほれ やじ馬どもをなんとかしろ！
They're verifying IDs
over at the tent!
消防署[しょうぼうしょ]:fire station, 員[いん]:member, テント:tent, 身元[みもと]:person's identity/ID/past, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation, 行う[おこなう]:to perform/to do/to conduct oneself
（消防署員３）テントのほうで
身元の確認を行っています
消防署[しょうぼうしょ]:fire station, 員[いん]:member, 道を空ける[みちをあける]:to make way for/to make room for|to pave the way for, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（消防署員４）
道を空けてください
Clear the way!
義父[ぎふ]:father-in-law|foster father|stepfather
（小源太）お義父(とう)さん？
（サリバン）ん？
Father?
大丈夫ですか？
Are you all right?
娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman), 離婚[りこん]:divorce, 成立[せいりつ]:coming into existence/arrangements|to come into existence
娘との離婚は成立したんだ
My daughter's divorce with you went through.
You have no business calling me "Father" now.
義父[ぎふ]:father-in-law|foster father|stepfather, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||, 筋合い[すじあい]:reason/right
“お義父さん”と
呼ばれる筋合いはない
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing, 考え直す[かんがえなおす]:to reconsider/to rethink/to reassess, 約束[やくそく]:promise|convention|destiny
う… 仕事を見つけたら
考え直してくれる約束でしたよね
You promised that you'd reconsider
if I found a job, though, right?
I set up a
marriage meeting!
見合い[みあい]:formal marriage interview/marriage meeting
見合いしたんだよ！
I did it to make sure that she wouldn't get
involved with another piece of trash like you!
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 引っ掛かる[ひっかかる]:to be caught in|to stop by|to get mixed up in (trouble)||
今度こそ お前みたいなクズに
引っ掛からないように
見合い[みあい]:formal marriage interview/marriage meeting, マリッジ:marriage, ミーティング:meeting
お見合い！？
マリッジミーティング…
A marriage meeting?!
She could've been happy if she hadn't
married the likes of you!
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 結婚[けっこん]:marriage, 幸せ[しあわせ, しやわせ]:happiness/good fortune/luck
（サリバン）
お前みたいなのと結婚しなければ
幸せになれたんだ
ホテル:hotel, 見合い[みあい]:formal marriage interview/marriage meeting, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 済む[すむ]:to finish|to merely result in something less severe than expected|to feel at ease|
ホテルで見合いなんて
しなくて済んだんだよ
Then we wouldn't have had
a marriage meeting at this hotel!
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
ううっ…
あっ まさか まだ あの中に
Wait... Are you telling me
that she's still in there?!
You lowlife!
You and your toys!
このクズが！
おもちゃ:toy/plaything
こんな おもちゃ
一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 幸せ[しあわせ, しやわせ]:happiness/good fortune/luck, 忍法[にんぽう]:ninja arts
女一人 幸せにできないで
何が忍法だ！
What good are you and your ninpo if they
can't even make one girl happy?!
You! You! You pauper! You screwup!
貧乏人[びんぼうにん]:poor person/pauper/the poor
この この この貧乏人
能[のう]:talent/gift|noh (theatre), 無し[なし]:without|unacceptable/not alright, 虫けら[むしけら]:worm/insect, 穀潰し[ごくつぶし, ゴクつぶし]:good-for-nothing/parasite/deadbeat
能無し 虫けら 穀潰し
You nobody! You loafer!
- Chieftain...
金[おうごん, こがね]:gold, 金[かね, かな]:money|metal, 地位[ちい]:(social) position/status, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.)
金も地位も仕事もなくて
その上 忍者だと？
You've got no money,
no social standing, and no job, and on top of all that,
you think you're a ninja?!
You think you can call yourself
a husband?!
夫[つま]:wife|my dear|garnish (esp. one served with sashimi)|, 夫[おっと]:husband, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
そんなものが夫と呼べるか！
You lowlife! Lowlife! Lowlife!
このクズが クズが クズが！
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
ああっ…
（タナベ）愛があります
He has love!
（サリバン）ええっ…
Even if he's a ninja,
even if he's got no money, if he's got love,
it'll work out in the end!
たとえ:example|simile/metaphor, たとえ:even if/no matter (what)/if, 忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.), お金[おかね]:money
（タナベ）たとえ忍者でも
お金がなくても―
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
愛があれば大丈夫です
No matter what kind of social standing or
fortune you've got, if you don't have love, you're a failure
as a husband!
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 地位[ちい]:(social) position/status, 財産[ざいさん]:property/fortune/assets, 愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 夫[つま]:wife|my dear|garnish (esp. one served with sashimi)|, 夫[おっと]:husband, 失格[しっかく]:disqualification/elimination/incapacity (legal)
どんなに地位や財産があったって
愛がなければ夫として失格ですよ
Who in the world
are you?
（サリバン）誰なんだ？ 君は
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 耳[みみ]:ear|hearing|edge|, ごちそう:feast/treating (someone)|to treat (someone, e.g. to a meal)
愛があれば
パンの耳だってごちそうです
If you've got love, even the ends
of a loaf of bread are a feast!
Even if she has
fancy dresses, it won't make her happy if a man she loves doesn't see her in them!
豪華[ごうか]:wonderful/gorgeous/splendor, ドレス:dress
（タナベ）豪華なドレスだって―
愛する[あいする]:to love, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me), うれしい:happy/glad/pleasant
愛する人に見てもらえなくちゃ
うれしくないでしょう？
愛する[あいする]:to love, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me), うれしい:happy/glad/pleasant
愛する人に見てもらえなくちゃ
うれしくないでしょう？
頭領[とうりょう]:head/chief/boss
（紅右近）頭領？
- Chieftain...?
愛する[あいする]:to love, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me), うれしい:happy/glad/pleasant
愛する人に見てもらえなくちゃ
うれしくないでしょう？
I can do this
on my own.
一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried
俺一人でいい
俺たち クズじゃないですよね
We aren't lowlifes,
are we?
くのいち:female ninja|woman
くのいちは １人より２人でしょう
Two kunoichis are better
than one, right?
見せる[みせる]:to show/to display, 忍法[にんぽう]:ninja arts, 底力[そこぢから]:latent energy/reserve strength/potentiality
見せてやりましょうよ 忍法の底力
Let's go show 'em!
Let's show 'em
what ninpo can do!
ヘッ バカどもが
You bunch of fools.
Why won't you understand!
Say something, Chieftain!
あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
どうして
分かってあげないんですか
頭領[とうりょう]:head/chief/boss
頭領さんも 何か言って…
あれ？
Huh?
（チッタ）ううっ んっ んあっ
Darn it, who the heck
cut the power?!
電源[でんげん]:source of electricity/electrical power|power (button on TV, etc.), 落とす[おとす]:to drop|to clean off (dirt, makeup, paint, etc.)|to lose (a match)||
もう 電源 落としたの誰よ
厨房[ちゅうぼう]:kitchen/galley|(Internet) troll, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
厨房にあった
（チッタ）早く 早く
I found this
in the kitchen!
Hurry! Hurry!
キャーッ
Let's go. The place is already
filling up with smoke.
かなり:considerably/fairly/quite, 煙[けむり, けぶり]:smoke/fumes, 回る[めぐる]:to go around|to return|to surround|, 回る[まわる]:to turn|to visit several places|to function well|
行くぞ もう かなり煙が回ってる
（チッタ）うっ… うん
Level E Control Room calling
all police cars on patrol...
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||, 有効[ゆうこう]:valid/effective|yuko (judo)
（小源太）一本
（三次）有効
Full point!
Quarter point!
効果[こうか]:effect/effectiveness|effects (e.g. sound effects, visual effects, special effects), 技[わざ, ぎ]:technique/art/skill
（紅右近）効果
（チュン）技あり
Eighth point!
Half point!
場外[じょうがい]:outside the hall (or stadium, market, etc.)/off the grounds/off the premises, 指導[しどう]:leadership/guidance|shido (disciplinary action for a minor infringement of the rules of judo)
（幻之丞）場外
（地雷也）指導
Out of bounds!
Foul!
（消防署員）おっ？
頭領[とうりょう]:head/chief/boss, 無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, 階段[かいだん]:stairs/stairway/staircase, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
頭領 ここは無理です
別の階段 探しましょう
Chieftain, this way's no good.
Let's look for another stairway.
うーん:hmm/well
（一同）うーん…
ええい やっ！
とおっ ほっ てあっ
（一同）おお！
続く[つづく]:to continue|to continue (without a break)|to occur again and again||
（紅右近）俺たちも続くぞ！
（一同）おう！
Let's follow
his lead!
Yeah!
The scene of the fire is adjacent
to the redevelopment area,
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, すげえ:incredible/unbelievable
（男性１）すげえ
Oh, wow!
Looks like that hotel had
second-rate firefighting equipment.
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, ホテル:hotel, 防災[ぼうさい]:disaster prevention, 装置[そうち]:equipment/installation/apparatus, 甘い[あまい]:sweet-tasting|fragrant (smelling)|lightly salted||, 甘い[うまい]:skillful|delicious|fortunate, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
（男性２）あのホテル
防災装置 甘かったらしいぜ
...and with the upcoming maintenance work, the
advance of emergency vehicles is hampered...
ん？
（チッタ）んっ…
駆け抜ける[かけぬける]:to run past from behind/to run through (e.g. gate, one's mind), 煙に巻く[けむにまく, けむりにまく]:to confuse someone/to befuddle someone/to create a smokescreen
よせ！
駆け抜ける前に 煙に巻かれる
Forget it! The smoke would overpower us
before we could get through!
But there's smoke everywhere!
There's nowhere to go!
煙[けむり, けぶり]:smoke/fumes, いっぱい:one defeat, いっぱい:amount necessary to fill a container (e.g. cupful, spoonful, etc.)/drink (usu. alcoholic)|full, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places
でも どこも煙でいっぱいで
もう行く所が…
（ハチマキ）あっ…
ああ…
（チッタ）何？
What is it?
ちゅう:kiss|squeak (as in the sound made by mice), ちゅう:annotation/explanatory note/comment, 房[ふさ]:tuft|bunch (of grapes, etc.)|section (of an orange, etc.), 房[ぼう]:chamber|home of a monk|Chinese "room" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
ちゅう房に戻るぞ
（チッタ）ええ？
Back to the kitchen!
面[おもて, おも]:face|surface|mask (esp. a noh or kyogen mask), 面[つら]:face|surface|surrounding area|
お面！
Point!
胴[どう]:trunk|plastron (in kendo)|frame (of a drum, etc.)
（チュン）胴 胴 胴
Face strike!
小手[こて]:gauntlet (used in Kendo)/bracer/fencing glove, 小手[こて]:forearm
（幻之丞）小手 小手 小手…
（紅右近）のさぁ
Veranda!
Sliding door!
ふすま:fusuma/Japanese sliding screen, ふすま:wheat bran/mash
（地雷也）ふすま
Bamboo screens!
（三次）あれ～
なっ… うっ
娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman), 降りる[おりる]:to descend (e.g. a mountain)|to alight (e.g. from bus)|to step down||
（サリバン）娘が…
娘がまだ降りてきてないんだ
My daughter! My daughter
hasn't come down yet!
忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.)
忍者もです！
Other ninjas!
道を空ける[みちをあける]:to make way for/to make room for|to pave the way for, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（消防署員）
道を空けてください 道を空けて
Clear the way, please!
Clear the way!
（小源太）うっ ぐうっ
Chieftain!
頭領[とうりょう]:head/chief/boss
頭領
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 煙[けむり, けぶり]:smoke/fumes, 吸う[すう]:to smoke|to suck|to absorb|
（小源太）うっ 大丈夫だ
少し煙を吸っただけだ
I'm all right...
I inhaled a little smoke, that's all.
後ろ[うしろ]:back/behind/rear, 煙[けむり, けぶり]:smoke/fumes, 塞がる[ふさがる, ふたがる]:to be closed|to be clogged|to be occupied
後ろも煙で塞がっちまったよ
The way back is blocked
with smoke, too...
Is this... Is this
the end for us?
ここまで…
ここまでなのか
あっ
（ハチマキ･チッタ）
ハァ フゥ ハァ フゥ…
（一同）ああっ
（ハチマキ･チッタ）
ハァ フゥ ハァ フゥ…
That's hot!
あっちい
（チッタ）ハァ フゥ…
おりん おりんか？
O-rin!
O-rin, is that you?!
小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|
小源太！
Kogenta?!
Huh? The ninjas?
What're you doing here?
忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.)
（ハチマキ）
あれ？ 忍者？ どうして？
ハチマキ:headband, 妻[つま]:wife|my dear|garnish (esp. one served with sashimi)|, 妻[め]:female/woman|wife
（小源太）
ハチマキさん あんたが妻を？
Hachimaki-san?
You saved my wife?
おかげ:grace (of God)/benevolence (of Buddha)|assistance, 過[か]:surplus- (attaches to start of Sino-Japanese words)/excess-|per- (chemical with more of a certain element than found in other compounds of the same constituents), 酸化[さんか]:oxidation/oxidization, 石灰[せっかい, いしばい]:lime/quicklime/caustic lime, 製剤[せいざい]:formulation (of pharmaceuticals)/preparation/pharmaceutical production
いや こいつのおかげだよ
過酸化石灰製剤
No, we have these
to thank.
A solution of
calcium peroxide.
要する[ようする]:to need/to demand/to take, 植物[しょくぶつ]:plant/vegetation, 肥料[ひりょう]:manure/fertilizer/fertiliser, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||, 酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), 発生[はっせい]:outbreak|generation (e.g. of power or heat)|ontogeny
要するに植物の肥料を水に入れると
酸素が発生するんだ
Basically, if we add it to the fertilized water
for the plants here, it generates oxygen.
ちょうど:exactly/precisely|as if, ちょうど:supplies/furniture/fixtures, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 電磁[でんじ]:electromagnetic, 用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, セラミック:ceramic, 鍋[なべ]:saucepan/pot|stew
ちょうどいい所に
電磁用のセラミック鍋もあったしな
We were lucky that they also had some
ceramic pots for their microwave, too.
Now that you mention it, Ai-chan did mention
that you were astronauts...
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot
そういや
愛(あい)ちゃんが宇宙飛行士だって
Oh, I get it! They're like
homemade spacesuits.
手製[てせい]:handmade, 宇宙服[うちゅうふく]:space suit, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods
そうか
お手製の宇宙服みたいな物か
All we need to do now is head back
the way you came in, and we should be able
to get out of here.
道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, 脱出[だっしゅつ]:escape/break-out|prolapse
（ハチマキ）
あとは あんたらの来た道を戻れば
なんとか脱出できる
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||
無理だよ この道は―
We can't. The way back is...
We can't go back that way now.
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
俺たちも戻れなくなったんだから
（ハチマキ）ええっ！？
So you're saying that there's
nowhere to run?!
逃げ場[にげば]:refuge/escape
じゃあ 逃げ場なしってこと？
What did you come
here for, then?!
結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go
あんたら 結局 何しに来たのよ！
忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.), 不可能[ふかのう]:impossible
いや 大丈夫だ
忍者に不可能はない！
No, we'll be fine!
Nothing is impossible for a ninja!
（一同）ええっ！？
とっとと:quickly/at once/right away, 娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman), 助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|
あんたらプロだろ
とっとと娘を助けろ！
You people are professionals, aren't you?!
Get in there and save my daughter!
服[ふく]:clothes (esp. Western clothes)|counter for doses of medicine, gulps of tea, drags of a cigarette, etc., 服[ぶく]:mourning clothes|mourning/period of mourning, 貸す[かす]:to lend/to loan|to rent out, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
その服 貸してください
私が行きます
Give me your suit!
I'll go in, too!
服[ふく]:clothes (esp. Western clothes)|counter for doses of medicine, gulps of tea, drags of a cigarette, etc., 服[ぶく]:mourning clothes|mourning/period of mourning, 貸す[かす]:to lend/to loan|to rent out, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
その服 貸してください
私が行きます
ああっ
（タナベ･サリバン）ええっ？
我[われ, わ]:I|oneself|you|, 我[わが]:my/our/one's own, 忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.)
（一同）我ら 忍者８人衆！
We!
Are!
The Ninja Eight!
えっ？
（一同）んんっ
（消防署員）にん… じゃ？
Ninjas...?
You're kidding!
Even at 1/6 G, it's still...
もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance
もしかして―
いくら:how much?/how many?|even, まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
いくら６分の１Ｇだからって
まさか…
They wouldn't!
火山[かざん]:volcano
風林火山
Wind, woods,
fire, mountain!
大化[たいか]:Taika era (645.6.19-650.2.15), 改新[かいしん]:reformation
（一同）大化の改新
The Reforms of
the Taika Era!
全席[ぜんせき]:all tickets
満漢全席！
Chinese royal
full-course banquet!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
やめてー！
Don't do it!
Ultimate secret technique!
最終[さいしゅう]:last/final/closing, 奥義[おうぎ, おくぎ]:secret techniques/inner mysteries/esoterica
最終奥義
霞[かすみ]:haze (esp. in spring)/mist|dimness (of sight), 忍法[にんぽう]:ninja arts, 大宇宙[だいうちゅう]:macrocosmos/macrocosm/the universe, ムササビ:Japanese giant flying squirrel (Petaurista leucogenys), 変化[へんか]:change|variety|inflection|, 変化[へんげ]:shapeshifting (of an animal or spirit)|incarnation|transformation
霞忍法 大宇宙ムササビ変化(へんげ)
Mist ninpo! Form cosmic
flying squirrel!
（一同）ああっ
You've gotta be
kidding me...
んな バカな
いくら:how much?/how many?|even
いくら６分の１だからって
Even at 1/6 G,
they're still gonna...
忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.)
忍者！
Ninjas!
Ninjas?
女性[じょせい, にょしょう]:woman/female|feminine gender, 忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.), 男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender
（女性１）忍者？
（男性１）忍者だって？
Did he say ninjas?
It's ninjas!
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, 忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.), 女性[じょせい, にょしょう]:woman/female|feminine gender
（男性２）忍者だ
（女性２）えっ？
Ninjas?
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, 忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.), 女性[じょせい, にょしょう]:woman/female|feminine gender
（男性３）忍者だ
（女性３）忍者…
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, 忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.)
（男性４）忍者だよ
It's ninjas!
人々[ひとびと, にんにん]:each person/people/men and women, 歓声[かんせい]:cheer/shout of joy
（人々の歓声）
Ninja!
忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.)
（一同）
忍者！ 忍者！ 忍者！ 忍者！
忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.)
（ハチマキ）ハハハッ
忍者 アハハハッ
Ninja!
Boy, landings sure are tough,
aren't they?
着地[ちゃくち]:landing, 難しい[むずかしい, むつかしい]:difficult|fussy|gloomy||
（三次）
いやあ 着地って難しいんだね
地面[じめん]:ground/earth's surface, 着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow, 途端[とたん]:just (now, at the moment, etc.)/just as/in the act of, 一気[いっき]:chug!/drink! (said repeatedly as a party cheer), 体重[たいじゅう]:body weight/one's weight, かかる:to span/to bridge/to cross, かかる:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang
（地雷也）地面に着いた途端
一気に体重がかかるんだもんな
Yeah, your weight hits you all
at once when you touch down...
What the hell is going on here?! Well?!
どういう:somehow/how/in what way
（ハチマキ）どういうことなんだよ
これは ああ？
だって ハッちゃん
If I had told you it was a marriage meeting,
would you have agreed to go, Hachi?
見合い[みあい]:formal marriage interview/marriage meeting, 受ける[うける, ウケる]:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||
見合いって言ったら
受けてくれないでしょ？
Of course not! As if
I'd ever get married!
当たり前[あたりまえ]:natural/reasonable|usual, 結婚[けっこん]:marriage, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
当たり前だ！ 誰が結婚なんて
娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman), 不足[ふそく]:insufficiency/shortage/deficiency
うちの娘じゃ 不足だってのか？
Are you saying that my daughter's
not good enough for you?!
Father, I'll make her happy,
so you don't have to worry!
義父[ぎふ]:father-in-law|foster father|stepfather, 幸せ[しあわせ, しやわせ]:happiness/good fortune/luck
お義父さん
僕が彼女を幸せにしますから
別れる[わかれる]:to part (usu. of people)|to separate (of a couple)|to lose (e.g. one's mother)
だから あんたとは別れたの！
Get it straight!
We're divorced!
忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.)
忍者って言ったら 才蔵(さいぞう)でしょ？
And a real ninja name
is something like "Saizou!"
What kind of name
is "Kogenta"?!
小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, センス:taste (in fashion, music, etc.)/sense (e.g. of humour)/flair
小源太なんて センスないんだから
Chief, how many months is the lease
on my apartment for?
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, アパート:apartment building/apartment block/apartment house, か月[かげつ]:months (period of), 契約[けいやく]:contract/compact/agreement
課長 私のアパート
何か月契約なんですか？
When are you gonna
move in, Ai-chan?
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 越す[こす]:to cross over (e.g. mountain)|to go over (e.g. with audience)|to pass time (e.g. a winter)||
愛ちゃん いつ越してくんの？
For now,
it's for two years.
取りあえず[とりあえず]:first of all/at once|for now, 礼金[れいきん]:finder's fee/reward|key money, 無駄[むだ]:futility/uselessness/pointlessness
取りあえず２年
礼金とか無駄になっちゃうからさ
The deposit would've gone
to waste, otherwise.
How about "Shooting Star Ai"?
流れ星[ながれぼし]:shooting star/falling star|star (white patch on the forehead of a horse), 愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
“流れ星の愛”なんて どうかな？
くのいち:female ninja|woman
（タナベ）あっ いや
くのいちは ちょっと…
Come on, I'm not
your kunoichi.
Do you have a paring knife
or something?
果物[くだもの, かぶつ]:fruit, ナイフ:knife, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
果物ナイフとか持ってない？
I have a throwing knife,
if that'll work.
持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
くないなら持ってるけど
Hey, they said that those
aren't allowed in here!
持ち込み[もちこみ]:bring-your-own (e.g. food and drink)/carry-on (e.g. luggage), 禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban
あっ 持ち込み禁止って
言われてんのに
He's treating my daughter like dirt
just because she's a divorcee!
娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman), バツイチ:being once divorced/one-time divorcee/one x mark, i.e. one name struck from the koseki, 軽い[かるい, かろい]:light (i.e. not heavy)|light (i.e. of foot)|non-serious||, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
うちの娘がバツイチだからって
軽く見やがって
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 見合い[みあい]:formal marriage interview/marriage meeting, 件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item
星野さんで
宇宙お見合い 49件目なのよ
Hoshino-san makes her 49th Space Marriage Meeting.
ええ？
The next one will be 50 even!
Let's do it next time!
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, ちょうど:exactly/precisely|as if, ちょうど:supplies/furniture/fixtures, 件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item
（仲人）次なら ちょうど 50件目
次にしましょう 次に
うるさい:noisy/loud|annoying
おりんちゃん
（チッタ）うるさい
O-rin-chan~
Go away!
Ninpo Flying Pillow!
忍法[にんぽう]:ninja arts, 飛ぶ[とぶ]:to fly/to soar|to jump, 枕[まくら]:pillow/bolster|introduction (e.g. to a rakugo story)
忍法 飛び枕！
Ninpo Flying Pillow Catch!
忍法[にんぽう]:ninja arts, 枕[まくら]:pillow/bolster|introduction (e.g. to a rakugo story), 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
忍法 枕取り
術[じゅつ]:art|means|trick|, 術[すべ]:way/method/means
（地雷也）枕返しの術
Ninpo Flying Pillow Return Technique!
枕[まくら]:pillow/bolster|introduction (e.g. to a rakugo story)
（幻之丞）枕ホマミキサー
It's a bitter pillow
to swallow!
先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), まっくら:total darkness/pitch dark|bleak future
（チュン）お先 まっくら
Go pop a pillow!
また…
Here we go again...
（ハチマキ）はあ～あ
ぐうっ
ぐあっ くっ…
Ninpo is hereby
forbidden!
忍法[にんぽう]:ninja arts, 禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban
忍法は禁止だー 禁止！
It's banned!
♪～
飲み干す[のみほす]:to drink up/to drain (cup)
♪グッと水を飲み干し
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
夕焼け[ゆうやけ]:evening glow/red sunset/afterglow (of sunset), 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
♪今日も一日が終わって
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
街路樹[がいろじゅ]:roadside trees, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood), テンパる:to become one tile away from completion|to be at one's wits' end/to be about to blow one's fuse
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, つまずく:to stumble/to trip|to fail
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
気楽[きらく]:carefree/comfortable|easygoing
♪気楽にいこうぜ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
愛する[あいする]:to love, 勇気[ゆうき]:courage/bravery/valour, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 叩く[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 叩く[はたく]:to dust|to slap|to use up money
♪新しいドア叩いて
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
歩く[あるく]:to walk
♪ひとつひとつ
歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
♪君も僕もすべての人も
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
喜び[よろこび]:joy/delight/rapture, 悲しみ[かなしみ]:sadness/sorrow|affection, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), つづける:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
Next Time
Extraterrestrial Girl
（ハチマキ）何だ？ これ
What's this?
お見舞い[おみまい]:calling on someone who is ill/enquiry/inquiry, リンゴ:apple (fruit)
（タナベ）
お見舞い リンゴです
A get-well gift. It's an apple.
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 離れる[はなれる]:to be separated|to leave|to leave (a job, etc.)|
（ハチマキ）俺たちは
地球から離れては―
We humans can't live
away from the Earth.
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good
生きていけない
That's just the way it is
right now.
現実[げんじつ]:reality/actuality/hard fact
それが 今の現実だ
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, ハチマキ:headband, 海[うみ, み]:sea/ocean/waters
（ノノ）見てみたいな
ハチマキの海
I sure would like to see
your ocean, Hachimaki!
全く[まったく]:really|indeed|good grief (expression of exasperation), 最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 若い[わかい]:young|immature|low (number)
（ローランド）
全く 最近の若いのは―
I swear, kids nowadays
aren't worth their salt.
だらしない:slovenly/loose/sluttish
だらしないな
なかなか:very/considerably|by no means (with negative verb), 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
（ノノ）２人だと
なかなか終わんないの
With just two people, it takes
forever to finish a game.
勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily, 引退[いんたい]:retire
俺を勝手に引退させるな
Don't you dare force me
to retire, you hear?!
ハチマキ:headband, 海[うみ, み]:sea/ocean/waters
（ノノ）どう？ ハチマキ
私の海
What do you think, Hachimaki?
This is my sea!